Boker Tov. Okay, yeah, today today's דף Daf is כ״ב, Chaf-Bet, we
pick up in the middle of כ״א עמוד ב׳, Chaf-Aleph Amud-Bet, and
what we had been dealing with is a shift from people of
great merit again. Now, we haven't really even gotten to חוני המעגל
Choni HaMa'agel in the discussion of the משנה. Mishnah. To me, that
story sort of dominates and is in the background, why I might
be projecting because the גמרא Gemara hasn't even introduced it yet. But
regardless, we have been dealing with stories of like other great people
and their merits, or sometimes their problems, like the guy who was
by the river and then said כמה מכוער אתה Kama Mechuar Atah
and so on. But nevertheless, most recently, we've been dealing with the
story about who was it, רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar
Ahava, who they took to in order to protect them from falling
walls and falling buildings, and there's ניסימא Nisima of falling walls and
falling buildings, and we've had נחום איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu who
protected the building from falling in. But in that context, it's important
to appreciate the shift here. First of all, those people are very
different than נחום איש גמזו, Nachum Ish Gamzu, number one, even those
great... no, I'm sorry, than חוני המעגל, Choni HaMa'agel, things we've pointed
out before, number one. But more than that, what we're dealing now
with the shift is from great people like אחד בדורו, Echad BeDoro,
amazing, amazing people, to what the גמרא Gemara recently has dealt with,
which is anonymous people doing small deeds of kindness and the power
that that has as well. And there's really a profound shift of
moving away
from the type of model that's being set out by a... thank
you, by
a חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agel or even by these other great people
who were different than חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agel but still like, as
I said, great individuals. Here it's anonymous people, small deeds. So, the
שומשני Shumshani was a whole neighborhood was saved from pestilence because of
a person who lent out the shovels for people to dig graves
and so obviously pestilence causes death so there's like a מידה כנגד
מידה Midah KeNeged Midah there. The whole neighborhood was saved from fire
because of a woman who shared her heated up oven, obviously another
type of מידה כנגד מידה Midah KeNeged Midah and that's now sort
of the theme that we're in. So with this we pick up
in the following way.
Okay, where were we?
Beginning of a line, אמרו ליה. Amru Leh. Okay, thank you, אמרו
ליה. Amru Leh. So about ten lines down in the wide
line, אמרו ליה לרב יהודה,
Amru Leh
LeRav Yehuda, they said
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, אתו קמצי, Atu Kimtzei, so the locust
has
arrived, so locust is about to come, and we know that's one
of the things you make a תענית Taanit and maybe even all
the neighboring places, the whole country makes a תענית. Taanit. Anyway, locust
is on its way.
גזר תעניתא, Gazar Taanita, he made a תענית. Taanit. אמרו ליה, Amru
Leh, they said to him, לא קא מפסדן, Lo Ka Mafsidan, you
don't have to worry, it's not really going to affect us.
So I don't know why they somehow felt that it wouldn't make
a difference. So, but they felt they weren't concerned about it. What?
They were far away, right? Presumably we're assuming they were far away.
And so that's getting back to that aspect of the משנה Mishnah
about even distant places, it would seem, but it's not explicit. Thank
you. אמר להו, Amar Lehu, he said to them, זוודא אייתו בהדייהו?
Zavda Aisu Bahadehayehu? Maybe they brought like a lunch with them? So
meaning, what do you mean? Oh, you feel those, it's not going
to affect us? Believe me, they're going to destroy the crops. The
only way it won't affect you is if they're bringing lunch with
them. So trying to make people appreciate, don't trivialize what the concern
is. אמרו ליה לרב יהודה, Amru Leh LeRav Yehuda, they said, that
was once with רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. Then people said to רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, איכא מותנא בחזירי, Ika Motana BeChazirei, there is a
pestilence among the pigs.
גזר תעניתא, Gazar Taanita, he made a תענית. Taanit. So that's something
that he felt presumably could spread to humans. So it's a similar
story of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda being sensitive to the way that
these things could
affect outside of the realm you think they might affect. So, נימא
קסבר רב יהודה מכה משולחת ממין אחד משולחת מכל המינים? Neima Kasavar
Rav Yehuda Makat Meshulachat MiMin Echad Meshulachat MiKol HaMinim? That once a
plague is spread amongst one species, it'll spread to another
species? So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
שאני חזירי דדמיין מעייהו לבני אינשי. Shani Chazirei DeDamyan Ma'ayeihu Livnei Inshi.
So no, maybe it's not a general statement that it spreads from
one species to another, but maybe specifically pigs, their intestines are similar
to human intestines, and therefore I don't know why they thought this
was specifically something, maybe it was something specifically that afflicted the intestine.
Anyway, this is the type of thing that they could think crosses
species from pigs to humans, but we shouldn't necessarily generalize that we
assume everything does this.
Right, I mean most, I mean like AIDS was because it crossed
over from monkeys, right? Wasn't it? Yeah, I mean some of the
most terrible diseases are the ones that have crossed the species line.
Swine
flu, yeah. Swine flu, yeah. Bird flu comes from birds. There you
go, right.
And hate to be elegant about
it.
How...? How do you know? Maybe he was wrong. That was his
assumption.
And maybe, and they could know things by empirical, by observation, even
if they didn't understand the underlying science.
I see.
Only our methods for knowledge are allowed to survive.
I'm not saying that.
Anyway, alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so,
alright. אמר ליה לשמואל, Amar lei leShmuel, they said to שמואל. Shmuel.
That was רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. This is שמואל. Shmuel. This is
שמואל, Shmuel, רב יהודה'ס Rav Yehuda's רבי. Rebbe. So let's see what
שמואל Shmuel did. איכא מותנא בחוזי, Ika mosana beChuzai, there is a,
you know, a plague, pestilence in חוזי, Chuzai, which is a place.
So גזר תעניתא, gazar ta'anisa, presumably, yeah, somewhere distant. So he made
a תענית. ta'anis. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, מרחקא,
merchaka, isn't it distance? מרוחק? meruchak? אמר, Amar, he said, ליכא מעברא
הכא דפסיק ליה? leka ma'abra hacha depasik lei?
So there is no, what is it, you know, is there is
there is there is there some type of a crossing that's going
to stop it from coming? So like, you know, okay, who cares
if it's distance? The thing will still spread. There's nothing that's going
to prevent it from getting here.
So again, a point of going back to the theme of the
משנה Mishna about the surrounding areas that have to fast and the
thing about the concern of spreading, although, if you do, if you
remember, and this is something the גמרא Gemara will revisit, that one
of the things that was not in the list of things that
you do the distant places was דבר, dever, right? It said, where
was it? It said, where was it? וכן עיר שיש בה דבר
ומפולת אותה העיר מתענה ומריעה וכל סביבותיה מתענות ולא מריעות. Vechein ir
she-yesh bah dever u-mapoles, oso ha-ir misanis u-masria ve-chol sevivosav misanis velo
masrios.
So the immediate surroundings by דבר, dever, but not the places where
it says you you're מתריעין בכל מקום matri'in bechol makom wasn't דבר.
dever. So דבר dever was a thing which they felt was only
the nearby locations. So again, this is presumably something that שמואל Shmuel
that they felt was not nearby enough and שמואל Shmuel said there's
nothing that's going to stop it from spreading here. We're nearby enough.
There's not enough of a distance for us not to worry about
it. Okay. אמר ליה לרב נחמן, Amar lei leRav Nachman, they said
to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, איכא מותנא בארץ ישראל. ika mosana be-Eretz
Yisrael.
There's a, there's a מותנא, mosana, you know, דבר, dever, there's the
plague in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So גזר תעניתא. gazar ta'anisa. So
now we're going from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל. Bavel. Now
that's a real big jump because again in the משנה Mishna even
the things that said בכל מקום, bechol makom, you didn't know how
much it meant בכל מקום. bechol makom. Did it mean everywhere in
the same country? Did it mean if it's in China you have
to do it in France? So here, דבר, dever, which in the
משנה Mishna is only immediate surroundings, here he's making a תענית ta'anis
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל. Bavel. So let's take a
look. So אמר, amar, he said, אם גבירה לוקה שפחה לא כל
שכן? im gvira lokesh shifcha lo kol she-ken? So if the, if
the, you know, if the mistress of the house is being smitten,
will the maidservant not certainly? So right, it's not exactly clear like
that, so he sees this a little bit might, a little bit
more exactly like, you know, metaphysically, or you know, religiously. If ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael is being punished, we'll be punished as well, not
necessarily that naturally something would spread so much of a distance. So
then the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to analyze this. The גמרא Gemara says
טעמא דגבירה ושפחה. ta'ama degvira ve-shifcha. That's because of, you know, the
the mistress of the house and the maidservant. הא שפחה ושפחה, Ha-shifcha
ve-shifcha, if it was the maidservant and the maidservant in one place
in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz to another place in חוץ לארץ, Chutz
La'aretz, לא, lo, you would not do a תענית ta'anis for this
דבר. dever. ואמרו ליה לשמואל, Ve-amru lei le-Shmuel, didn't they say to
שמואל Shmuel איכא מותנא בחוזי ika mosana be-Chuzai וגזר תעניתא? ve-gazar ta'anisa?
That the immediate surroundings we just had, which was all in בבל,
Bavel, all in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, that because of דבר dever
in חוזי Chuzai he made a תענית? ta'anis? So the גמרא Gemara
says שאני התם כיון דאיכא שיירתא דלווי ואתיא בהדיה בהדיה. shani hasam
keivan de-ika shayrusa d-levai ve-asya ba-hadya ba-hadya.
So there it's different since there are caravans, it accompanies it and
comes with the caravan. So here you go, it really, you know,
sounds like they understood, right, but they understood that people are going
to carry the disease with them. There's actually a lot of travel
between those places and that reflects back שמואל'ס Shmuel's statement which is
there's nothing that is going to, you know, no like type of
a river or across some type of a thing that's going to
prevent the disease from spreading because there's regular travel. Right, that's also
part of the problem nowadays, right, with international travel and plane travel,
etc., how diseases are able to spread. So basically what you have
is the following. The משנה Mishna says דבר dever you only do
in the immediate surroundings. So we have two stories of non-immediate surroundings
where they make a תענית ta'anis for דבר. dever. One from one
place in בבל Bavel to another, which is presumably not considered to
be the immediate surroundings, and the other's ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to
בבל. Bavel. So ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל Bavel is explained
in some sort of religious metaphysical way, okay, but the two distant
places in בבל Bavel is explained by saying, you know, it's not
just about actual physical distance. If there's actually a lot of travel
between the two places, then that's a place that we have to
reasonably be concerned it's going to spread to. Okay, so even though
דבר dever in the משנה mishnah seems to be a more limited
concern, here the גמרא gemara is recognizing that it actually could spread
a great deal if there's travel between the places. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara talks about that would seem to be an interesting
interlude because now we resume the theme of talking about
less-than-prestigious people and the tremendous merit that even
the less-prestigious people carry. So let's take a look.
אבא אומנא, Abba Umna, אבא Abba the bloodletter, הוי אתי ליה שלמא
ממתיבתא דרקיעא כל יומא. hava asi leh shlama mimesivta derakia kol yoma.
Every day he would get a greeting from the heavenly ישיבה. yeshiva.
So somehow in his dream or whatever, something would appear to him
every day and say,
שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, he would get some type of a welcome
from the heavenly retinue every day. כל יומא. Kol yoma. ולאביי כל
מעלי יומא דשבתא, ule'Abaye kol malei yoma deShabsa,
אביי Abaye would only get a greeting from the heavenly ישיבה yeshiva
every ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. ולרבא כל מעלי יומא דכיפורא, ulerava kol
malei yoma deKippura, and רבא Rava would only get it every ערב
יום כיפור, erev Yom Kippur, once a year. So here you get
again, notice this point. I mean first of all there's the interesting
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava issue, which you might remember other גמרות
Gemaros speak about like how אביי Abaye lived sixty years and רבא
Rava only lived forty years because אביי Abaye was עוסק בתורה וגמילות
חסדים, osek beTorah u'gemilus chasadim, רבא Rava only in תורה. Torah. But
first of all there's an interesting question of why did אביי Abaye
get more merit, more welcome by the heavenly retinue than רבא? Rava?
That's one question. But the bigger problem issue is this guy we
never heard of is getting a greeting every day. And again it's
raising this theme of the small, more anonymous people and they have
tremendous merit. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara elaborates on this.
Okay, הוי קחלשא דעתיה דאביי משום דאבא אומנא. havy k'chalsha daiteh d'Abaye
mishum d'Abba Umna. So apparently this was known: who got greeted on
a monthly basis, on a daily basis, on a weekly basis, on
an annual basis? So
אביי Abaye felt
despondent that this אבא אומנא Abba Umna person, this
bloodletter, is on a higher level than he is. אמרו ליה. amru
leh. So they, presumably the heavenly retinue, said to him: לא מצית
למיעבד כעובדיה. lo masis leme'evad k'ovdeh. You can't live up to his
deeds. Why can't you live up to his deeds? ומאי הוי עובדיה
דאבא אומנא? umai hava ovdeh d'Abba Umna? What were his deeds? דכי
הוה עביד מילתא, dechi hava avid milsa, when he would עביד מילתא,
avid milsa, a phrase which means literally he would do a thing,
but what it means is he would let blood. When he would
let blood, הוה מחית גברי לחוד ונשי לחוד. hava machis gavrei lachud
u'nashei lachud. He would sit, like he'd have a separate room for
the men and a separate room for the women because presumably you're
going to be exposing areas of the body to do bloodletting, so
it would not be צניעות tzniyus to do them in the same
room. ואית ליה לבושא דאית ביה קרנא דהוה בזיע כי כוסילתא. ve'is
leh levusha d'is bei karna d'hava bezi'a ki kusilsa.
And he would have a special garment, like a robe that they
would put on for an examination robe, and it would have a
horn where they would let blood through horns which the blood would
come out of. And it was a slit by the shoulder. So
basically it was a garment that he could let the blood for
the women. It was a garment for the women without having to
expose their body. It had already a pre-made hole and a slit
exactly where he needed to insert the horn, and the horn was
pre-inserted. כי
הות אתיא ליה איתתא, ki havas asya leh ittessa, and when a
woman would come, הוה מלביש לה, hava malbish lah, he would dress
her with this robe, כי היכי דלא נסתכל בה, ki heichi d'lo
nistakel bah, that he should be able to do the letting of
the blood without looking at her uncovered body. ואית ליה דוכתא דצניע
דשדו ביה פשיטי. ve'is leh duchta d'tzni'a d'shadu bei pshitei. And that
was one thing, the צניעות tzniyus and the separating of the men
and women for themselves that they shouldn't see one another and that
even he as the professional should not have to see more than
he needed to see. ואית ליה דוכתא דצניע, ve'is leh duchta d'tzni'a,
and he had a private place דשדי ביה פשיטי, deshadi bei pshitei,
that people would put little coins there,
דשקיל, deshakil, that he would take for his services. So people would
pay for services, they'd put money in a box as they would
be leaving. No one would see, he wouldn't collect it directly, you
pay as you leave and in this box nobody sees. דאית
ליה שדי ביה, de'is leh shadi bei, and if you had the
money for the service you put it in the box. דלית ליה
לא מיכסיף, deleis leh lo michsif, and if you didn't have you
wouldn't be embarrassed, you wouldn't have to pay if you weren't able
to pay. וכי הוה מקלע ליה צורבא מרבנן, vechi hava mikla leh
tzurva me'rabbanan, now when he had a צורבא מרבנן tzurva me'rabbanan Torah
student come for his services, אגרא
מיניה לא שקיל, agra mineh lo shakil, he didn't ask for any
fee at all. Even if the person had money, he said, professional
courtesy, he didn't ask for any fee even if he could afford
it.
ובתר דקאי, u'vasar d'ka'i, and after the Torah student got up and
was done with his bloodletting, יהיב ליה פשיטי, yahiv leh pshitei, he
would actually give the student money. ואמר ליה, ve'amar leh, and he'd
say to him, זיל ברי נפשך, zil barei nafshach, go take care
of yourself, go buy yourself a nice meal, especially after you let
blood, you may be a little bit hungry, so he... exactly. Not
only would he not charge them, he would even give them money.
So יומא חד, yoma chad, so that's how, so that's his amazing
doings. Now again, you know, okay, it's not like, you know, oh
my god, completely unheard of, and it's actually quite interesting that they
say to אביי Abaye you couldn't do something like this. Now maybe
he wasn't a blood letter, maybe he didn't have the opportunity to
do that type of a thing, but again it's very, you know,
I think these stories are profound that these sort of like the
general type of basic like ישרות yashrus that can infuse your daily
life and how profoundly, you know, significant that could be and the
tremendous amount of זכות zchus that could come from that. So
יומא חד, yoma chad, so שדר אביי זוגא דרבנן למיבדקיה. shadar Abaye
zuga d'rabanan l'mivdakeih. So one day אביי Abaye sent two students to
check him, to check how righteous he really was. אביי Abaye was
still, you know, needed some, some deeper understanding of why he got,
why he had so much merit. So אוסבינו, osvinu, so he welcomed
the students, he sat them down,
ואכלינו ואשקינו, v'achlinu v'ashkinu, so presumably not only did he let, let
blood, but he invited, he fed them, he gave them to drink,
ומחצינהו בביסתרקי v'mchatsinhu b'bistarkei for which he like, he phylellia, he folded
up some nice, you know, cloth garments for them to sleep on
at night. לצפרא l'tzafra in the morning,
כרכינו ושקלינו, karchinu v'shaklinu, they took, they wrapped up this beautiful silk,
it wasn't silk, wool, whatever it was, anyway these beautiful expensive bedding,
and like, you know, you go to a, like people go to
nice hotels and they take what's in the, you know, the robes
or whatever. So they went ahead and after all of this good
he did, like they were testing him, they basically stole the bedding.
וקמו ונפקו לשוקא v'kumu v'nafku l'shuka and they went out to the
marketplace. ואשכחינו v'ashkachinu and then they found him in the marketplace and
they specifically, they wanted to like see, you know, how he would
react. So אמרו ליה amru leh they went to him and they
said, לשיימי מר היכי שוו, l'shimei mar heichi shavu, they said, hey,
you know, אבא אומנא, Abba Umna, you know, no, yeah, like they
said, what's his name, אבא אומנא, Abba Umna, they said, hey, Mr.
אבא אומנא Abba Umna or Doctor אבא אומנא, Abba Umna, we've got
these gorgeous sheets and bedding, how much do you think they're worth?
So, you know, we'd like to buy them, but could you give
us a price estimate on them?
So היכי שוו. heichi shavu. אמר להו הכי והכי amar lehu hachi
v'hachi such and such. אמרו ליה ודילמא שוו טפי amru leh v'dilma
shavu tfei they said, how do you know, maybe it's worth more?
אמר להו בהכי שקלינו amar lehu b'hachi shaklinu no, I know it's
worth that much, that's how much I paid for them. So he
knew that they were stolen, but he didn't say anything about it,
right? He didn't say thief, thief! He answered their question. So אמרו
ליה דידך נינהו ושקלינו מינך, amru leh didach ninhu v'shaklinu minach, you're
right, they're yours and we took them from you. אמרו ליה במטותא
מינך amru leh b'matusa minach they said, at your leave, like please
explain to us, במה חשדתין b'mai chashtin what did you suspect us
of when you realized we had stolen it and here we are
these Torah scholars, what did you think was up? אמר להו amar
lehu he said, אמינא פדיון שבויים איקלעו להו לרבנן amina pidyon shvuyim
iklu lehu l'rabanan I assumed you had some tremendous need for funds,
there was like captives that need money raised to be redeeming them,
וכסיפא למימר לי v'chisifa l'meimar li and you were embarrassed to directly
ask me for funds and but you were doing it in order
to use it for this מצוה. mitzvah. Now there wouldn't be allowed
גזל gezel obviously, but somehow he explained like he wasn't going to
think they're a runner, there must be some tremendous need that justifies
what they're doing. So אמרו ליה amru leh they said to him,
השתא נשקלינהו מר hashta nishklinhu mar okay fine, we did it to
test you, but take them back. אמר להו amar lehu he said
to them no, מההיא שעתא אסחתינהו מדעתאי לצדקה me'hahu sha'ata aschtinhu m'datai
l'tzedakah from that moment that I assumed you were going to use
them for פדיון שבויים, pidyon shvuyim, in my mind I had already
given them over to צדקה, tzedakah, so I don't want to take
them back, give them to צדקה. tzedakah. Okay, so there you see
again how this, you know, this tremendous righteousness in the, in the,
in an average quote unquote person.
So, you know, I just have to say this evokes two stories.
One story is they say of the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim that
he was once, that he was once, you know, had to testify
in court about something. So, like to about some other case. Anyway,
so the lawyer said to the judge, he says, I want you
to know the nature of the man standing before you. They say
about him that once some people came, you know, to, you know,
some poor people came and he invited them in his house and
he had them stay the night. And then in the middle of
the night, you know, they took his like silver, you know, candlesticks,
his silver, and they ran off with it. And he woke up
in the morning, he realized what had happened and he ran after
them and he said, and he said, אני מוחל, ani mochel, אני
מוחל, ani mochel, אני מוחל ani mochel because he didn't want them
to transgress the prohibition of theft. So the judge said to the
lawyer, he said, do you really believe that story? So the lawyer
said, actually I don't, but let me tell you something, they don't
tell stories like that about me and you.
So that's one story, which is almost very similar. The other story
I gotta tell you is, so here he is, he gives the
rabbinic students professional courtesy, right? And then אביי Abaye sends these two
students to check him out, so which is reminds me of the,
of the joke that this dentist, yikes, so a priest goes to
the dentist and after the dentist takes care of him, he says
like how much do I owe you? So the dentist says no
charge, professional courtesy. So a week later the priest sends him a
gold cross. So then a minister goes to the dentist, says, "How
much do I owe you?" "No charge, professional courtesy." A week later
he sends him a leather-bound Bible. So then a rabbi goes to
the dentist, "How much do I owe you?" So he says, "No
charge, professional courtesy." Week later sends him two rabbis.
So so here look אביי Abaye sends him two rabbis. Anyway, so
my I have a brother-in-law who's a dentist and he actually gave
professional courtesy to some people in the some the the whole ישיבה
yeshiva in his neighborhood and next thing he knew he was getting
everybody from the ישיבה. yeshiva. So it's really true. Anyway, alright, so
moving on. You had a question? Yeah.
"Well, just any comment about the the lack of righteousness of אבא
Abba and the rabbis?
Sorry, אביי." Abaye.
Oh, so we're going to look at אביי ורבא. Abaye and Rava.
Oh, you mean why they stole that?
Yeah, I mean they send people to test him.
Yeah, so that's an interesting question too. Like was that were they
over on גזל? gezel? They really have intention to steal it? Like
is it really, I mean that's an interesting question like how is
he allowed to do that even as a test? Okay, but so
that's definitely worth exploring more deeply. Let's take look now at the
difference between אביי ורבא. Abaye and Rava. Okay, הכי קחלשא דעתיה דרבא
משום דאביי. hachi kachalsha da'atei de-Rava mishum de-Abaye.
So now רבא Rava felt bad that אביי Abaye got a greeting
every week and he only got it once a year. So אמרו
ליה, amru leh, so they in the heavenly retinue said to רבא,
Rava, מסתייך, mistayecha, it is to be sufficient for you דמגני זכותך
אכולא כרכך, de-mageni zachutach akula karchach, you your merit protects the entire
city. So remember before I think we had that they said that
we didn't need, was that who was that that was, oh that
was רב. Rav. Anyway, so again we have this idea of protecting
the entire city, but again it doesn't really explain the idea that
אביי Abaye seems to be getting you know more honor than he
does.
"Wait, wasn't אביי Abaye protecting the city too?"
Yeah, exactly. Okay. And but again we're getting to this idea of
protecting you know the merit and protecting the city, which again would
suggest that the people higher up on this hierarchy אביי Abaye and
this אבא אומנא Abba Umna would protect even more. So again it's
this issue about do we really know who's where on the hierarchy
and what merit of even simple you know or anonymous and non-famous
individuals.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this, רב ברוקא חוזאה Rav Beroka
Choza'ah הוה שכיח בשוקא דבי לפת. hava shechiach beshuka de-Be Lapat. So
this person רב ברוקא Rav Beroka from חוזאה Choza'ah from was
would commonly go to the marketplace in בי לפת Be Lapat and
this is again going to be continuing the theme of like people
that you would have you know you don't even know about that
have tremendous merit. והוה שכיח אליהו גביה, ve-hava shechiach Eliyahu gabeih,
אליהו Eliyahu would commonly you know accustom himself with you know constantly
be encounter רב ברוקא. Rav Beroka. So obviously he's very he's very
righteous, he gets a regular visitations from אליהו. Eliyahu. אמר
ליה, amar leh, so he said to אליהו, Eliyahu, איכא בהאי שוקא
בר עלמא דאתי, ika behai shuka bar alma de-ati, is there somebody
in this marketplace that is a בר עלמא דאתי bar alma de-ati
worthy of the world to come? Presumably he meant out you know
not including myself. I mean I don't know if he was asking
about himself but presumably he wasn't. Anybody else in this marketplace other
than me that's deserving of the world to come?
אמר ליה, amar leh, לא, lo, no. Okay, אדהכי והכי חזא להו
גברא, ad hachi vehachi chaza lehu gavra,
as they were walking and waiting, all of a sudden oh he
saw a certain person אליהו Eliyahu דהוה סיים מסאני אוכמי de-hava siyem
masanei ukmei that was wearing black shoes, which presumably is not the
Jewish practice, ולא רמי חוטא דתכלתא בגלימיה ve-lo rami chuta de-techeleta bigleimei
and he did not have the תכלת techelet string in his garment,
which presumably means he wasn't wearing ציצית. tzitzit. אמר ליה, amar leh,
and אליהו Eliyahu said to רב ברוקא חוזאה, Rav Beroka Choza'ah, האי
בר עלמא דאתי הוא, hai bar alma de-ati hu,
this guy who doesn't even look Jewish is a בן עולם הבא.
ben olam haba. רהט בתריה, rahat batrei, so
רב ברוקא חוזאה Rav Beroka Choza'ah ran after him. אמר ליה, amar
leh, מאי עובדך, mai ovdach, what are your deeds? Tell me what
your deeds are what you know what you do that's meritorious. אמר
ליה, amar leh, זיל אידנא ותא למחר, zil idna ve-ta lemachar, so
he says I can't answer you, come back tomorrow. Okay, ולמחר אמר
ליה u-lemachar amar leh the next day he says to him מאי
עובדך, mai ovdach, what are your deeds? אמר ליה, amar leh, זנדוקנא
אנא, zandukna ana, I am a זנדוקנא zandukna which by context and
רש"י Rashi says presumably means a like a somebody who is a
prison guard. ואסרנא גברי לחוד ונשי לחוד ve-asarna gavra lachod ve-nashi lachod
and when a prisoners come to me I lock up the men
in one section and the women in another section. So to prevent
you know immoral behavior and as we know happens in prisons as
well and possibly also to prevent rape. ורמינא פורייא, ve-ramina puraya, so
again there's that interesting sort of theme about צניעות tzniut as an
important issue.
ורמינא פורייא ve-ramina puraya
and we'll see about that in a minute. And I put my
bed בין הני להני bein hanei lehanei between the two sections כי
היכי דלא ליתו לידי איסורא ki heicha de-lo leitu lidei issura that
there should be no sin that should occur, transgression that should occur.
כי חזינא בת ישראל דיהבי נכרים עלה עיניהו, ki chazina bat Yisrael
de-yahvei nochrim ala einaihu, now when I see a בת ישראל bat
Yisrael who's being put into prison and that the non-Jews are have
put their eye upon her and that she you know and that
she actually could be raped by them, מסרנא נפשאי ומצילנא לה, masarna
nafshai u-matzilna lah, I am willing to risk my own life you
know or sacrifice myself in order to save her. Maybe not literally
but whatever I'm willing to whatever needs to be done. in order
to protect her. יומא חד הויא נערה מאורסה גבן yoma chad hava
naara me'orasa gavan once there was a betrothed woman by us, a
young betrothed woman, דיהבו בה נוכראי עינייהו deyahavu bah nuchra'ei eineihu that
the non-Jews were you know putting their eye on her where you
know clearly they had evil intentions about her. שקלי דורדייא דחמרא shakli
durdaya dechamra
I took the dregs of the wine ושדאי לה בשיפולה veshadai lah
beshipulah
and I put it on the hem of her cloak. ואמרי ve'amri
and they saw this and they said אשתנא היא ishtana hi she's
a נדה. niddah. Yeah
she's menstruating and therefore presumably they had a revulsion of not wanting
to have sex with her while she was menstruating and that way
you know without having to put myself but you know directly put
myself between them I managed to avoid the problem you know to
protect her. So אמר ליה amar lei מאי טעמא לית לך חוטייא
ורמית מסני אוכמי mai ta'ama leit lach chutaya veramit masanei uchmei why
are you not wearing ציצית tzitzit and wearing black shoes? So אמר
ליה amar lei he said to him עיילנא ונפיקנא ביני נכרים ayeilna
venafikna beini nuchrim because I go in and out
between you know amongst the amongst non-Jews
כי היכי דלא לידעו דיהודאה אנא ki heichi delo leidu diyuhada'ei ana
so that they won't know that I'm a Jew. כי הויא גזירתא
ki hava gezeirata and when they you know so presumably and I
travel in certain circles where where I hear
certain things and when I hear that they've made an edict you
know against the Jews מודענא להו לרבנן modana lehu lerabanan I let
the Rabbis know about this ובעו רחמי ומבטלי לגזירתייהו uvau rachamei umvatli
legezeirataihu
and they pray and annul the decree. It's interesting that the Rabbis
pray rather than other types of means of you know more pragmatic
interference like we've seen before.
Is it a דאורייתא de'oraita then for...
Yeah well that is... Oh you mean about the ציצית? tzitzit? Yeah.
Yeah first of all it's interesting it only mentions תכלת. techelet. Does
תכלת techelet mean ציצית tzitzit and it's just using תכלת techelet to
represent ציצית? tzitzit? Does it mean in general people had tassels on
their garments which might very well be and what makes ציצית tzitzit
unique was not the fact that there were tassels but the fact
that it was a blue string? What? It's interesting that it mentions
specifically or could תכלת techelet just be represent... But yes there actually
is discussions about that about people that are קרוב למלכות karov lemalchut
has to do with other issues around like בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem and other
cases where they speak about somebody like you know where he was
בלורית blurit he was מגדל בלורית megadel blurit etc. other types of
things that the you know that have special categories related to like
קרוב למלכות karov lemalchut that allows certain latitudes. But anyway but we're
not trying to justify it halakhically so that's not like the conversation.
Let's let's finish the story okay. Okay and so okay.
So now the גמרא gemara says okay ומאי טעמא כי אמינא לך
אנא מאי עובדך אמרת לי אתא למחר umai ta'ama ki amina lach
ana mai ovdach amrat li ata lemachar
why when I first asked you did you not answer me you
say come back tomorrow? אמר ליה amar lei דבההיא שעתא גזור גזירתא
devahei sha'ata gezar gezeirata
no because at that moment I had just heard that there was
an edict that had been decreed אמינא ברישא איזיל ואשמעינהו לרבנן דליבעו
רחמי עלה amina bereisha aizil ve'ashmeinhu lerabanan delivau rachamei alah I had
to set my priority straight let me first go tell the Rabbis
and let them pray for it I'm not going to spend my
time answering this guy here. דמילתא דהכי והכי. demilta dehachi vehachi. Okay
so therefore and that's why I couldn't answer you. It's a little
bit interesting right because it at least in my mind evokes the
earlier story about נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu who said
wait and he was punished. Here he said wait but it was
the right thing. Here it was a wait because he had the
priority straight. Presumably נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu said wait
and he had his priorities not straight you know he should have
figured out how to give the guy food without making the guy
wait. Yeah.
By the way it's like אלישע Elisha and גיחזי Geichazi you know
take my cloak don't speak to anybody
here he is a cloak-bearer not speaking to anybody. That's a good
point too. Right that's a good point too. So I think that
the power of this story here is you know it even goes
further
than the issue of like the anonymous people as I'm as I've
been saying and the you know and the people you but here's
somebody that actually you would look and say
this guy what a sinner like he's not even dressing Jewish he
doesn't wear a כיפה kippah he doesn't wear ציצית tzitzit like you
know the type of people that you know the most unlikely person
that you would think might be the person with the greatest merit.
Right? So it's a really powerful sort of story about who do
we assume you know are the people with you know with merit
and who are the people you know you know that like this
in this context you know can save people because of their deeds
like before we had you save people you were so righteous that
you saved the wall from falling down and that's sort of been
the theme until now here here's somebody that number one not only
is like anonymous he's somebody דווקא davka you would think is like
a sinner somebody you would never think it and number two the
way he saves people is very pragmatically right he saves people by
protecting the women by you know putting by putting his bed between
them by doing certain things by telling the Rabbis you know so
his sort of his saving is not just by his metaphysical merit
it's actually by his actual this type of worldly deed and again
I think all of this creates an interesting contrast to like you
know what's his name to חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agel the exact opposite
extreme of all of this. Let's finish the story. אדהכי והכי adehachi
vehachi you know
during that whole conversation or as things were passing אתו הנהו תרי
אחי atu hanu terei achei some have the version תרי אחי trei
achei or or two brothers came or two people came אמר ליה
amar lei and so either it's two brothers and then אליהו Eliyahu
said to him or two people came And then אליהו Eliyahu went
and said to him, anyway, הני נמי בני עלמא דאתי, hani nami
bnei alma de'ati, these two also are getting עולם הבא. Olam Haba.
מאן אינו? Man innu? אזל לגבייהו, Azal legabeihu, he went to them.
אמר להו מאי עובדייכו, Amar lehu mai ovdeichu, what is it that
you do? אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, אינש בדוחי
אנן, Inash beduchei anan, we're jesters. מבדחינן עצבי, Mevadchinan atzvei, we make
sad people laugh.
אינמי כי חזינן בי תרי דאית להו תיגרא, Inami ki chazinan bei
trei de'it lehu tigra, if we see two people that are fighting
בהדייהו bahadeihu with one another, טרחינן ועבדינן להו שלמא. tarchinan ve'avdinan lehu
shlama. So, you know, we lighten up the whole atmosphere and we
do, you know, we gesture around and we get them to make
peace with one another by trying to, you know, to encourage more
laughter and positive feeling. So this גמרא Gemara apparently was quoted a
lot in the early Chassidic literature, you know, about the power of
like laughter and joy and you get עולם הבא Olam Haba even
like the simple person by bringing laughter into life and so on.
But again, people that you would think are the most like lowly
and marginal in society, the ones you completely dismiss, clowns, jesters, and
here again their deeds are actual deeds that are in very practical.
It's not like before we started with deeds like I never leave
the בית מדרש, Beit Medrash, I'm always you know I don't go
you know very much like in the religious type of realm and
here these are the deeds that are very pragmatic in terms of
making a difference in people's lives. Yeah, first point.
Did you think that אליהו Eliyahu says, "Oh yeah, really nobody here
has been עולם הבא? Olam Haba? What about כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא?" Kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek l'Olam Haba?
Okay, so that's a good question. That כל ישראל יש להם חלק
לעולם הבא Kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek l'Olam Haba excellent question is
a later line added to the
משנה, Mishnah, which is not standard rabbinic theology. Standard rabbinic theology is
צדיקים tzaddikim have עולם הבא. Olam Haba. You know like that's what
we say about the whole thing about ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, צדיקים
נכתבים ונחתמים לאלתר לחיי עולם הבא, tzaddikim nichtavim venachtamim l'altar l'chayei Olam
Haba, רשעים reshaim you know גיהנום Gehennom and the בינונים beinonim are
תלויים ועומדים. tluyim ve'omdim. You know what you say to the גר
ger is you know when he converts is you say, "אין עולם
הבא אלא לצדיקים." Ein Olam Haba ela l'tzaddikim. Don't think just by
being Jewish you're going to get עולם הבא. Olam Haba. That thing
that we all like saying that's very reassuring to us, כל ישראל
יש להם חלק, Kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek, is actually a real
outlier in rabbinic theology and was added later to the משנה Mishnah
to start the מסכת סנהדרין Masechet Sanhedrin in a positive way. Yeah.
I would suggest it's not just the simple people, but it's interesting
that these are workers. They're working and because they're working they have
the opportunity or right, they don't have the opportunity because they're sitting
in...
Yeah, that's an interesting point. Like when they say to אביי, Abaye,
"You can't do like his deeds," doesn't mean that אביי Abaye wasn't
righteous enough to be able
to do that, but he doesn't have the opportunity to do it.
You're in the בית מדרש Beit Medrash all the time. You don't
have the opportunity to be doing these types of things. I think
that's an excellent point and thank you for making that. Right. So
that when they said to אביי, Abaye, "You can't live up to
it," it doesn't mean you're not as much of a צדיק tzaddik
as he is. But you're in the בית מדרש Beit Medrash and
this guy every single day, look how he's helping people. Yeah, I
appreciate that. That's an excellent point.
Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. על אלו מתריעין בכל מקום.
Al elu matri'in bechol makom. So we've already a little bit addressed
this about the idea of every place that has to be involved
in מתריעין matri'in doesn't necessarily mean fast, it's a little ambiguous in
the משנה. Mishnah. Minimally it means doing the special prayers. It might
very well mean the special prayers with the fast; there were different
meanings of that in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, but you know there
were some things that are in the immediate environs and then we
had the discussion that גבר gever might be even more distant places
because of travel and so on. But then the things that were
listed
in the משנה Mishnah were things like
שדפון וירקון, shidafon veyerakon, blight, jaundice, disease to the grain. It was
the ארבה וחסיל, arbeh vechasil, locusts, and those types of things were
things that would spread and you would do it everywhere. Okay. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, the Rabbis taught: על אלו מתריעין בכל מקום על
השדפון ועל הירקון. Al elu matri'in bechol makom al hashidafon ve'al hayerakon.
So right, the wind blasting of the grain and jaundice and disease.
ועל ארבה וחסיל ועל חיה רעה. Ve'al arbeh vechasil ve'al chaya ra'ah.
Locusts, various locusts, wild animals that are going in inhabited places. רבי
עקיבא אומר על השדפון ועל הירקון בכל שהוא. Rabbi Akiva omer al
hashidafon ve'al hayerakon bechol shehu. שדפון וירקון Shidafon veyerakon even the slightest
amount, you know, is you don't have to wait till it gets
to be a certain threshold. Even the slightest amount you fast everywhere
and you're מתריע matri'a in everywhere, you do the special prayers. That's
an indication of bad things to come. ארבה וחסיל Arbeh vechasil and
similarly the locusts, אפילו לא נראה בארץ ישראל אלא כנף אחד, afilu
lo nira b'Eretz Yisrael ela kanaf echad, even if what's seen in
the land of Israel only one locust, one literally one wing, מתריעין
עליהן, matri'in aleihen, would be enough for everybody to be involved in
the prayers and maybe the fast because they come in swarms. Exactly.
And disease also doesn't stay where it is, it spreads. Okay, it's
not clear if the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma disagrees or if רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is just clarifying. ועל חיה, Ve'al chaya, so the
wicked animals. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: חיה רעה שאמרו. Chaya ra'ah she'amru.
Not wicked, whatever, any wild animals but dangerous animals. בזמן שהיא משולחת
מתריעין עליה. Bizman shehi meshulachat matri'in aleiha. When it is a like
a problem that spreads, you know, it's not just a chance occurrence.
Well, we'll see what that means. It's not just a chance occurrence,
but it's something that's a traveling, spreading type of problem. Then you
do the, you call out, you do again, which means minimally saying
עננו Anenu in the תפילות, tefillos, might incorporate the idea of תפילות
tefillos as well, of תענית taanis as well. אינה משולחת, Eina meshulachas,
if it's not something that spreads, and it's maybe something that's more
chance, אין מתריעין עליה, ein matri'in aleha, you do not. איזוהי משולחת
ואיזוהי שאינה משולחת, Eizohi meshulachas ve-eizohi she-eina meshulachas, how do you determine
which is which? נראתה בעיר, Nir'asa ba-ir, משולחת. meshulachas. בשדה, Ba-sadeh, אינה
משולחת. eina meshulachas. So if you have a lion walking around in
the city, that's a problem. If you see them in the field,
it's not a problem. ביום, Ba-yom, משולחת, meshulachas, if they're traveling around
in the day, problem. בלילה, Ba-layla, אינה משולחת, eina meshulachas, night not
a problem. That's just standard. ראתה שני בני אדם ורצה אחריהם, Ra'asa
she-nei bnei adam ve-ratsa achareihem, if the animal will see two people
and run after them, משולחת, meshulachas, then you've got a problem because
normally might run after one person, but to run after two people,
now you've got a real wild animal on your hands, a real
uncontrollable animal. נחבאת מפניהם, Nechbes mifneihem, if it goes and hides from
the presence of two people, אינה משולחת, eina meshulachas, it is not
considered a problem that's spreading that we have to worry about. טרפה
שני בני אדם ואכלה אחד מהם, Tarfa she-nei bnei adam ve-achla echad
mehem, משולחת. meshulachas. If it, well we'll see how all these different
pieces fit together. If it attacked two people, killed two people, and
ate one of them, that's a problem. Okay, now only if it
ate zero or one it's a problem, but interestingly, somewhat ironically, if
it says אכלתה שניהם, achlasa sheneihem, אינה משולחת, eina meshulachas, ate both
of them, it's not a problem, because maybe it was hungry. So
just because it's hungry doesn't mean that it's on a rampage and
going in the, you
know, and
gonna attack other people. All right, so of course what even if
it comes in the city and kills two people, how does that
fit in with the other thing? Maybe that's only if it does
it in the forest, you know. So the גמרא Gemara will sort
of fit these pieces together in a
minute. Okay. עלתה לגג ונטלה תינוק מעריסה, Alta la-gag ve-natla tinok me-arisa,
משולחת. meshulachas. Okay, if it went up to the rooftop and had
grabbed an infant out of its cradle, I don't know what type
of dingo. Well anyway, exactly what animal we're talking about, that's a
problem. Okay. What? Dingos. Oh right, the dingos, right, yeah, yeah. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now the גמרא Gemara is
going to analyze all of this. הגופא קשיא. Ha-gufa kashya. Wait, we've
got an internal contradiction. אמרת נראתה בעיר משולחת לא שנא ביום ולא
שנא בלילה. Amarta nir'asa ba-ir meshulachas lo shena ba-yom ve-lo shena ba-layla.
First you said in the city it's a problem, which implies it
doesn't matter day or night, any time. והדר אמרת ביום משולחת בלילה
אינה משולחת. Ve-hadar amarta ba-yom meshulachas ba-layla eina meshulachas. It goes by
night or day. So which is it, you know, which of those
was an and and which of those was an or? So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא הכי קאמר. lo kashya hachi ka-amar. Here's
what it means. נראתה בעיר ביום משולחת. Nir'asa ba-ir ba-yom meshulachas. This
is interesting, you might have thought it would have gone the other
way, but it's only if the two things come together is it
a problem. In the city and in the daytime. That shows that
you've got this wild, untamed, you know, raging animal on your hands.
בעיר בלילה אינה משולחת. Ba-ir ba-layla eina meshulachas. Even if it's in
the city, if it only comes out at night and doesn't come
out in the day, you don't really have a huge problem yet
on your hands. אי נמי בשדה וביום, Ei nami ba-sadeh u-va-yom, if
you see it in the fields, you know, okay, maybe its normal
habitation is the forest but still it's not going into the city,
it's only in the field, so then even if it's in the
daytime, אינה משולחת, eina meshulachas, it's not a problem. It's only a
problem
if it's both walking around in the city and in the daytime.
But that's even if it didn't do anything. Remember the משנה Mishna
said even if it ראתה, ra'asa, right? You know, even if you
just see it. But if you see it in this way that
normally you would never see a lion walking around in the city
in the daytime, now you've got a problem. Now, ראתה שני בני
אדם ורצה אחריהם משולחת. Ra'asa she-nei bnei adam ve-ratsa achareihem meshulachas. So
if it runs after two people, it's a problem. The גמרא Gemara
says, what do you mean, why does it have to run after
two people? הא עומדת אינה משולחת? Ha omedes eina meshulachas? That sounds
like if it's just standing and not doing anything, it's not a
problem. והדר אמרת נחבאת מפניהם אינה משולחת, Ve-hadar amarta nechbes mifneihem eina
meshulachas, if it hides from them it's not a problem. הא עומדת,
Ha omedes, which implies that if it's standing and not hiding, there's
always that middle case, משולחת, meshulachas, it is a problem. The גמרא
Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בשדה הסמוכה
לאגם כאן בשדה שאינה סמוכה לאגם. Kan be-sadeh ha-smucha le-agam kan be-sadeh
she-eina smucha le-agam. So there's two scenarios in the fields. In the
fields if it's close to like the swamp or forest or not
close to a swamp. So here's basically the way it works. If
it's in a city, right in the middle of walking down Broadway,
you don't need it to do anything. Just that it appears in
the daytime in a city, that's a problem. If it's not in
the city, it's out in the field, it's only going to be
a problem if it does something. Now there are two scenarios. One
is the field near a forest. There, it's got the place to
hide near the forest, naturally it will be more bold, so then
it would only be a problem if it actually actively ran after
people. If it's in a field not near a forest, then even
if it just doesn't run away from people, you've got a problem,
because it's not near its sort of habitation and it's and it's
not running away,
presumably regardless. Okay, so there we have all these different gradations: city
just appearing, field either chasing or not running away depending if the
field is near the forest or not near the forest, all these
different gradations. Okay, now let's go on to the next case. טרפה
שני בני אדם כאחד ואכלה אחד מהם משולחת. Tarfa she-nei bnei adam
ke-echad ve-achla echad mehem meshulachas. If it... טרף שני בני אדם כאחד
ואכל אחד מהם המשולחת. Taraf shnei bnei adam ke'echad ve'achal echad mehem
hameshulachat. Kills two people and only eats one of them, it's a
problem; but if it eats both of them, it's not a problem.
Now, where is that taking place? שנים אינו משולחת. shnayim eino meshulachat.
האמרת אפילו רצה. ha'amarta afilu ratza. What do you mean? You said
even running after people is a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר פפא כי תני היא באגמא. Amar Pappa ki tani hi be'agma.
No, now we're talking about in the forest itself. So in the
field, where it's not its natural habitation, just running after people or
not running away from people shows you got a problem on your
hands. But if you actually surprise a bear in the middle of
the forest where it lives and it kills somebody
there, we don't send out a big alarm that a bear killed
somebody when they surprised the bear in its home in the forest.
So there it's only going to be a problem if it actually
killed somebody and did not eat the person because that shows that
this animal is not just about
eating for hunger. Of course, sometimes a bear will kill because it
thinks that
it's being attacked or that it's protecting its young, but anyway, you
understand the issues that the גמרא Gemara is dealing with. Okay. גופא
אף אלו לגבי דנטלה מינייהו עריסה משולחת. Gufa af elu legabi denatala
mineihu arisa meshulachat. If it takes an infant, it's משולחת. meshulachat. So
the גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא הכי עדיף? Pshita hachi adif? It's stealing
infants out of their cribs? So אמר רב פפא בקוכי דציידי. Amar
Rav Pappa bekuchei detzaidei. We're talking about a hide of hunters. That's
the thing that they do, a hide, where they sort of make
a little hole and they hide in the ground or whatever for
catching animals. Anyway, so somehow they had an infant in this little
hide. I don't know what they're doing taking their baby; if you're
going hunting with friends, you're taking
the baby. Anyway, so in that type of a scenario, maybe it's
not so crazy that it was stolen the baby out. So you
have to say that no, that's still a problem. All right, moving
on. That's wild animals. Then we also say
על החרב, al hacherev, on the sword, troops that are passing through,
that's another thing that בכל מקום, bechol makom, they're going from country
to country when armies are on the march and everybody has to
fast. Again, what's everybody, how much of the opposite sides of the
world do you have to do it, but that's not fully explained.
But anyway, troops is one of these things that are more universal.
So תנו רבנן חרב שאמרו אינו צריך לומר חרב שאינו של שלום.
Tanu Rabanan cherev she'amru eino tzarich lomar cherev she'eino shel shalom. And
it goes without saying that if you're actually dealing with troops that
are warring against countries, that you've got a problem. אלא אפילו חרב
של שלום, Ela afilu cherev shel shalom, even if they're not attacking
you. They're just passing through, getting safe passage through your land to
attack somebody else. Nevertheless, if the world's at war, even if they're
just passing through you right now, you got to start worrying. You
never know where it's gonna end. שאין לך חרב של שלום יותר
מפרעה נכה. She'ein lecha cherev shel shalom yoter miParoh Necho. You don't
have a better example of a sword of peace, just passing through,
than פרעה נכה, Paroh Necho, which as we'll see in the time
of King יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, that he was from מצרים Mitzrayim and he
wanted to pass through to do war with the nations on the
eastern side of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ואף על פי כן נכשל
בה המלך יאשיהו. Ve'af al pi chen nichshal bah hamelech Yoshiyahu. Nevertheless,
it was the stumbling of King יאשיהו Yoshiyahu and it led to
his death. שנאמר, Shene'emar, let's first read the story and then we
can talk about it. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the verse says:
וישלח אליו מלאכים לאמור. Vayishlach elav malachim lemor. And פרעה נכה Paroh
Necho sent messengers to יאשיהו Yoshiyahu saying: מה לי ולך מלך יהודה?
Ma li valach melech Yehuda? Because יאשיהו Yoshiyahu went out to sort
of stop them. It's actually an interesting inverse of what we've been
reading recently in דברים, Devarim, that ישראל Israel just wanted to pass
through מואב Moav and אדום Edom and they came and they blocked
their troops out and said you're not passing through. So here the
reverse happens, פרעה נכה Paroh Necho just wanted to pass through ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and יאשיהו Yoshiyahu went out with his troops and
said no, you're not passing through. So he says, look, what are
you doing getting involved in this? מה לי ולך? Ma li valach?
What do I have against you? What do you have against me?
We don't have any fight between us. לא עליך אתה היום. Lo
alecha ata hayom. I'm not coming to fight against you today. כי
אל בית מלחמתי. Ki el beit milchamti. I'm going to the place
I'm waging war. I'm just passing through here. ואלוהים אמר לבהלני. Ve'elohim
amar levahalani. And the God has said to urge me on my
way. So actually quoting God to King יאשיהו. Yoshiyahu. We'll see what
the גמרא Gemara does with that. חדל לך מאלוהים אשר עמי. Chadal
lecha me'elohim asher imi. You lay off from opposing not only me,
but God who is with me. ואל ישחיתך. Ve'al yashchitecha. And let
Him not destroy you. And the end of the story is that
יאשיהו Yoshiyahu ignored him and went to war and basically the archers
shot at יאשיהו Yoshiyahu and יאשיהו Yoshiyahu was brought back and he
was mortally wounded and he was brought back to his home and
he died. And that was the end of King יאשיהו. Yoshiyahu. So
which is actually something that comes up in a lot of the
קינות Kinot that we say, or some of the קינות Kinot that
we say on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So מאי אלוהים אשר עמי?
Mai elohim asher imi? So the גמרא Gemara first pauses to say,
what is this "God who is with me"? Like, what is פרעה
נכה Paroh Necho doing quoting God? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב זו
עבודת זרה. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav zu avoda zara. He didn't
really mean God. He meant god in the lowercase G, his god.
So אמר, Amar, so that gave יאשיהו Yoshiyahu a reason to think
that he should be opposing him. הואיל וקא בטח בעבודת זרה. Ho'il
veka batach be'avoda zara. Since he's putting his faith in this idolatry,
נכילינא ליה. Nachilina leh. I will be able to oppose him. ויורו
המורים. Vayoru hamorim. Now going back to the story, ויורו המורים למלך
יאשיהו. Vayoru hamorim lamelech Yoshiyahu. The archers shot at King יאשיהו. Yoshiyahu.
ויאמר המלך לעבדיו העבירוני כי החליתי. Vayomer hamelech la'avadav ha'avironי ki hechaleti.
take me away because I have, I'm like, I'm mortally wounded is
the meaning of that word in context, but the מאד, me'od, or
I am very ill, but obviously the ill doesn't do justice to
it. So the Gemara is going to say what does the word
hechalesi mean? מאי כי החליתי מאד? Mai ki hechalesi me'od? אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, מלמד שעשו כל גופו
ככברה. mela'med she-asu ko gufo ki-kivra. They made his body like a
sieve. It was like, you know, pierced with so many holes it
was like a sieve. Probably from the word like מחילות mechilot which
are like, you know, tunnels or holes or something like that. אמר
רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmeni
Amar Rabbi Yonatan, מפני מה נענש יאשיהו? mipnei ma ne'enash Yoshiyahu? Why
was יאשיהו Yoshiyahu punished? What did he do to deserve this? So,
such a righteous king? מפני שהיה לו לימלך בירמיהו ולא נמלך. Mipnei
she-haya lo limalech b'Yirmiyahu v'lo nimlach. He should have asked ירמיהו's Yirmiyahu
advice and he didn't ask his advice. מאי דרש? Mai darash? What
was יאשיהו Yoshiyahu thinking? He looked at the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק
pasuk says: וחרב לא תעבור בארצכם. V'cherev lo sa'avor b'artzechem. When you're
doing God's will, you'll get the blessing and no sword will pass
through your land. So he said to himself: Look, מאי חרב? mai
cherev? What type of sword are we talking about? אילימא חרב שאינו
של שלום? Ileima cherev she-eino shel shalom? If it means literally you
won't be attacked in battle, you know, war won't come to you?
וכתיב ונתתי שלום בארץ. V'chasiv v'nasati shalom ba'aretz. It already says that
there'll be peace in the land. So it goes without saying we
won't be attacked in battle. אלא, Ela, it must mean: אפילו של
שלום, afilu shel shalom, even a, even armies that are not waging
war among us, you know, we will be such a protected, you
know, country that people won't even pass through, pass through us to
go to another country. So therefore, and he felt: I'm a righteous
king, we're deserving of these blessings, I'm not going to let this
happen. והוא אינו יודע, V'hu eino yodeia, he did not know: שאין
דורו דומה יפה, she-ein doro domeh yafeh, that his generation was not
worthy. That's great, that's what the blessing was, but his generation was
not worthy of that, of that blessing. כי הוה ניח נפשיה, Ki
hava nayaich nafshei, when he was dying, cause then he was taken
away from the battlefield and he died in his bed. And when
he was dying, חזא ירמיהו שפוותיה דקמרחשן. chaza Yirmiyahu sifvasei d'kamrachshan. So
he saw his lips, the lips of יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, that were like
moving. אמר, Amar, so יאשיהו Yoshiyahu said, I mean ירמיהו Yirmiyahu said:
שמא חס ושלום מילתא דלא הגנא אמר. shema chas v'shalom milsa d'lo
hagna amar. Maybe he's saying something inappropriate? Like maybe he is complaining
against God, how could it be I was so righteous and this
terrible thing is happening to me? So ירמיהו Yirmiyahu wanted to know
what he was saying. אגב צעריה, agav tza'arei, because of his pain.
גחין ושמעיה דקא מצדיק עליה הדין. gochin v'shamei d'ka matzdik alei ha-din.
So he bowed down to listen closely and he heard that יאשיהו
Yoshiyahu was actually, you know, מצדיק הדין, matzdik ha-din, attesting to the
fact that God had done righteously. He wasn't complaining against God, he
was quite the opposite, whatever God does is just. ענה ואמר, Ana
v'amar, he said: צדיק הוא ה' כי פיהו מריתי. Tzadik hu Hashem
ki fihu marisi. Obviously, where does this whole idea that he was
whispering and ירמיהו Yirmiyahu listened and bowed down, that's like a big
departure from the verses, there's no hint to it. But what we're
seeing they're trying to do is to tie this story of יאשיהו
Yoshiyahu and ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, ירמיהו Yirmiyahu was not explicitly there, but he
was in the same time, to מגילת איכה, Megillas Eichah, which was
written by ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, and show how that's being reflected in מגילת
איכה. Megillas Eichah. So the line in מגילת איכה, Megillas Eichah, which
is צדיק הוא ה' כי פיהו מריתי, Tzadik hu Hashem ki fihu
marisi, God is righteous even though these terrible things have happened, the
destruction of the temple, whatever, God in the end is righteous. The
Gemara wants to see that as ירמיהו Yirmiyahu reporting what יאשיהו Yoshiyahu
was saying and bring this story into מגילת איכה. Megillas Eichah. פתח
עליה ההיא שעתא, Pasach alei ha-hi sha'ata, and therefore ירמיהו Yirmiyahu therefore
responded to him in the following way: רוח אפינו משיח ה', Ruach
apeinu mashiach Hashem, you know, so the our the whole the, you
know, God's anointed, our entire hope about, you know, this יאשיהו Yoshiyahu
would save us, we wouldn't be, the temple wouldn't be destroyed, finally
a righteous king and here and he was therefore trapped, you know,
and stumbled because of our sins. Like in the end the generation,
as the Gemara said before, maybe he was righteous but all the
sins of the generation ultimately brought down his downfall. And this by
the way, for people know, right, there's a קינה kina that begins
ויקונן ירמיהו על יאשיהו Vaykonen Yirmiyahu al Yoshiyahu that developed this whole
theme of here was their hope of salvation, you know, and he
could have been the משיח mashiach and he could have saved them
and prevented it, and in the end, you know, it's impossible to
fully escape, you know, when the whole generation has gone awry, you
know, you can't always escape that. Now how is this exactly relevant
to חרב שאינו של שלום? cherev she-eino shel shalom? I mean, you
could say: Okay, you know, it's not a problem, just if you
like give them free passage, you won't be, you know, why do
you have to fight? But the point is once troops are on
the march, you never know who's gonna get caught up in that,
you know, when people are going to war at once, you know,
you might start being an ally and then you become the next
country that's attacked. So you know, so things might look like no
big problem, you whenever there's a whenever people troops are marching, it's
a problem. Yeah, they're going to rape and pillage and plunder. Exactly.
And all the other things that troops do, right. Maybe they're not
going to actually attack your country, but as they're traveling through, they're
going to rape and pillage and plunder. Exactly. Now that isn't exactly
brought out from the יאשיהו Yoshiyahu story. The example isn't so great,
but the Gemara but anyway but you understand the concern about this,
yeah. But if you're writing as his drash was right, it would
have been חרב ששל שלום cherev she-shel shalom that even the ברכה
bracha still so that indicates but the only reason why it didn't
why wasn't blessed is because his generation wasn't worthy. Right. Right, right,
correct. I think just by asking the question why was he punished
implies that he was correct to try to stop. Right, that's I
think what Mike was saying. The fact that there has to be,
that there's a ברכה Bracha that you don't have even a חרב
של שלום Cherev shel shalom passing through shows that even a חרב
של שלום Cherev shel shalom is a problem. Right, exactly. But I'm
saying the fact that they're saying why was he punished implies that
his actions were, right, yeah, yes. And and see what everyone's assuming,
to me the sin of the generation was that they didn't support
him. They wanted the true gods to be able to... Oh, I
don't think so. I think other areas in חז״ל Chazal is basically
like, you know, people were still being עובד עבודה זרה Oveid Avodah
Zarah and whatever. I mean he was trying to uproot hundreds of
years of, you know, deeply ingrained going off the דרך. Derech. So
you know, that that was hard, you know. Other גמרות Gemaras I
think bear that out. Okay, let's read a little bit more. מעשה
בירדו הזקנים מירושלים לעריהם, Maiseh b'yardu hazekeinim m'Yerushalayim l'areihem, so there was
a story that the elders came from ירושלים Yerushalayim to their cities
and they made a תענית Ta'anis because there was seen a מלא
פי כבשן, Malei pi kivshan, the fill of the mouth of an
oven of, I think it was ירקון Yerakon in אשקלון, Ashkelon, of
this type of a diseased grain. So איבעיא להו, Iba'yu lehu, כמלא
תנור תבואה, Kemalei tannur tevuah, when they say the fill of an
oven, did they see, was it how much grain did they see
that was diseased? Remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said even a tiny
bit, but here it seems like there's a minimum amount. So or
at least according to them, how much, how much was it? Was
it an oven filled with grain, that much was diseased? או דילמא
כמלא תנור פת, O dilma kemalei tannur pat, the amount of grain
that would make bread to fill an oven? But that's obviously a
lot less grain than actually fills an oven, it's just the amount
of grain you would need because bread, you know, expands and whatever.
So תא שמע, Ta shma, come here, כמלא פי תנור, Kemalei pi
tannur, as a mouth of the oven. So you know, you could
have bread like sitting in the mouth of an oven, but if
you try to put grain in the mouth of the oven, it's
all going to spill. So it means bread. So the amount of
grain to get bread that would fill the mouth of an oven.
ועדיין איבעיא להו, Ve'adayin iba'yu lehu, we could still ask, ככיסויה דתנורא,
Kekisuyah d'tannura, enough bread to just fill the opening of the oven?
או דילמא כידרא דריפתא דהדרא ליה לפומא דתנורא? O dilma kidara d'rifta
de'hadra lei lephuma d'tannura? Is it stacked bread from the bottom of
the oven all the way to the mouth of the oven? Or
is it just bread in the mouth of the oven? תיקו, Teiku,
we don't know. But anyway, here you have a sense against רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that said even the slightest amount that there's some
minimum. So עוד גזרו תענית על שאכלו זאבים, Od gazru ta'anis al
she'achlu ze'evim, because these wolves ate these two kids, or here was
another version that just because they appeared and that goes back to
the גמרא Gemara we said before. Did they appear in the city?
Did they appear in the forest? You know, those types of issues.
אמר עולא משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Amar Ulla mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehotzadak, מעשה באו זאבים שני תינוקות Ma'aseh ba'u ze'evim shnei tinokot
ויקיאום דרך בית הראי. ve'kiyium derech beit ha're'i. There was this story
where two wolves consumed, devoured two children or two babies and they
excreted them. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים U'va ma'aseh lifnei chachamim and it
came before the חכמים, Chachamim, וטהרו את הבשר וטמאו את העצמות. ve'tiharu
et habasar ve'timu et ha'atzamot. So that's coming out of left field
and they were dealing with it from a טומאה וטהרה Tumah ve'taharah
perspective. So the meat that had been transformed into excrement was no
longer considered meat and was no longer טמא, Tamei, the bones were
still bones and therefore they were טמא. Tamei. So again, it's interesting,
but what I do have to say it's also doing is and
similar to the previous גמרא Gemara of exactly how much bread are
we talking about, wheat or bread or whatever, is we're getting in,
like think about the radical sort of shift of genre we did.
Not only from אגדה Aggadah to הלכה, Halacha, but even before when
we're talking about the הלכות Halachos of תענית, Ta'anis, they were much
more I would say like embracing the whole experience of what this
means, about what's happening and how we're responding into it, and here
we're very it's a very detached type of an analysis. Okay, let's
figure out exactly how much grain. What would be the status of
the bones of the kids that were excreted? I mean, it's very
clinical and detached, which is the standard sort of way הלכה Halacha
is operating. You know, I think that that's interesting considering that the
הלכה, Halachic, even the הלכה Halachic discussions that preceded seemed much more
engaged in the larger sort of religious experience of what was going
on. I don't know what to make of it, but it's certainly
interesting to note that type of a shift. Let's just try to
read a little bit more. על אלו מתריעין בשבת, Al elu matrin
be'shabbat, the following you can even do on שבת. Shabbat. It talks
about like if a city is being attacked or a river's overflowing.
תנו רבנן, Tanoo rabanan, עיר שהקיפוה אחרים או נהר ואחת ספינה המיטרפת
בים ואחד יחיד שנרדף מפני אחרים ומפני ליסטים ומפני רוח רעה, Ir
sheheikifuha achurim o nahar ve'achas sefina hamitarefet bayam ve'achas yachid shenirdaf mipnei
achurim umipnei listim umipnei ruach ra'ah, whether it's a city that's being
attacked or a boat that's about to tip over, you know, that's
about to caught in a storm, or somebody's being chased after by
אחרים Achurim or by robbers, ומפני רוח רעה umipnei ruach ra'ah or
an evil spirit, whatever that is, על כולן יחיד רשאי לסגף עצמו
בתענית. al kulan yachid rashai lehageif et atzmo beta'anis. The text really
should say, if you look at the side, מתריעין בשבת. matrin be'shabbat.
On these you would sort of have the special תפילה Tefillah on
שבת, Shabbat, point number one, which is what our משנה Mishnah says,
although it added a few things, and then it adds another point
to this which is ועל כולן יחיד רשאי לסגף עצמו בתענית. ve'al
kulan yachid rashai lehageif et atzmo beta'anis. A person is allowed to
לסגף lehageif himself, very interesting graphic description, לסגף lehageif yourself with a
fast because of these occurrences. רבי יוסי אומר אין היחיד רשאי לסגף
עצמו בתענית, Rabbi Yosei omer ein hayachid rashai lehageif et atzmo beta'anis,
let me just read it, אין היחיד רשאי לסגף עצמו בתענית, ein
hayachid rashai lehageif et atzmo beta'anis, you're not allowed to do this,
שמא יצטרך לבריות ואין הבריות מרחמות עליו, shema yitzarech labriyot ve'ein habriyot
merachamot alav, lest you need people and people are not merciful to
him. be people, you need other people because now you know you're
sickly and you're not healthy and you know you fasted and they
won't have compassion on you. Maybe they won't provide you food, maybe
because they'll feel you did it to yourself or maybe just סתם
stam they won't have compassion on you. You're not allowed to put
yourself in that situation. אמר יהודה אמר רב, Amar Yehuda amar Rav,
מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי, mai ta'ama de-Rebbi Yosi, what's the reason of
Rebbi Yosi? דכתיב, De-chtiv, ויהי האדם לנפש חיה, vayehi ha-adam le-nefesh chaya,
the person was a living soul. נשמה שנתתי בך, neshama she-natati becha,
the soul I gave you, החייה, hachaye, make sure to keep it
alive. So this is very interesting, like, what is this debate doing
here? This sounds like the general debate of is it
a good thing to make a תענית ta'anit or not?
So I would argue that what's going on and number one, what's
the חידוש chidush you're allowed to make a תענית? ta'anit? The whole
thing is not you're allowed as an individual to make a תענית,
ta'anit, so when we as a ציבור tzibbur have to make a
תענית. ta'anit. So number one, it's possible the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is saying even on שבת.
Shabbat. On שבת Shabbat we're not going to be גוזר gozer a
תענית ציבור, ta'anit tzibbur, but these things
which are so urgent,
the ship is about to sink, the city's about to be attacked,
if you as an individual want
to make a תענית ta'anit on שבת Shabbat you're allowed. So that
would explain why the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma has
to say you're allowed as an individual, because we're maybe we're talking
specifically on שבת. Shabbat. Similarly, Rebbi Yosi's opposition might be a general
opposition to doing a תענית, ta'anit, but it also might be
remember what Rebbi Yosi said in the משנה. mishna. Does anybody remember
what Rebbi Yosi said in the משנה mishna
about מטריעין matri'in on שבת? Shabbat? He said yeah, you can be
מתריע matri'a on שבת Shabbat if you want to call people to
help. You can't be מתריע matri'a to do special תפילות.
tefillot. And he might be saying the same thing here. The right
response if this is happening on שבת Shabbat is not for people
to fast. If people are fasting they're actually hurting the cause. Don't
fast, eat what you need to eat and take care of the
people of the city and of the and you know start putting
the sandbags up to protect the river from overflowing. So it could
be that he's not talking about a general sort of opposition to
fasting, but sometimes you don't pray and you don't fast, you act,
and that seems to be consistent with Rebbi Yosi in the משנה.
mishna. Okay, we will end here. Yes, I wrote a whole article
on that. It's one line, it was a line that was inserted
later in the משנה mishna that רש״י Rashi says it's not רש״י
Rashi in our גירסא girsa but the מהרש״א Maharsha quotes it, you
know, רש״י Rashi already testifies to the fact that that line was
added later so the משנה mishna wouldn't have to start by saying
אלו שאין להם חלק לעולם הבא, elu she-ein lahem chelek le-olam ha-ba,
so it was added as a nice way of intro you know
so it wouldn't start on a harsh point, but it really is
not at all standard within theology, I actually wrote an article on
it. Yeah, but that's what I say, what, כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא? kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek le-olam ha-ba? No, that's
what we say to become our practice. פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, that's
in פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. No, it gets reinforced. I don't know,
because we like telling ourselves that we're all going to get עולם
הבא. olam ha-ba. I don't know when, I don't know when it
started becoming part of I'm sorry, just you had a question. I
was gonna say something else. Also in addition to the homiletic utility
of stories of kindness by by people you wouldn't expect to have
a lot of merit blah blah blah, I wonder if in fact
there's something bigger than that and really validates the entire rabbinic enterprise,
by which I mean that fundamentally to me the rabbinic enterprise was
about it was about holiness and about making the argument that you
can live in the world and still be holy, which in contrast
to the Sadducees for example and all these other cultures, that's sort
of what it was about. And here are people who are living
in the world but acting in a holy way. Sure, every one
of those their acts were pure, absolutely pure and holy. So I
wonder if in a sense what they're saying this is what we're
all about, we're about living in the world, not necessarily locking up
ourselves up in a בית מדרש beit midrash and being the smartest
person around, but it's about about living holy lives, being holy in
the world. Right, I think that that's absolutely correct, and I think
that although the גמרא Gemara didn't expand it because it never told
us the difference between אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, why אביי Abaye
got a weekly visit and רבא Rava only an annual one, you
know, I think it goes back to another גמרא Gemara that says
that אביי Abaye lived to sixty and רבא Rava to forty because
אביי Abaye was עוסק בתורה וגמילות חסדים osek be-Torah ve-gemilut chasadim and
רבא Rava was just in תורה. Torah. So I think that that's
an excellent point. Yeah, יישר כוח, Yasher koach, thank you. Yeah, is
it unique to a מסכתא? masechta? Is it in כתובות? Ketubot? Or
did you just say the man's name and not of the father?
That's always those identifying another יוסי בן שמעון Yosi ben Shimon or
whatever right in the גמרא, Gemara, I mean we can do that
nowadays if necessary, but in the גמרא Gemara I think that it
was just
I'm just trying to figure hold on a second, in the גמרא
Gemara I think that it was just. It was just that it
was like unheard of to you know like like it would
be like you know before like a hundred years ago if somebody
would have said you know well why don't you consider going by
your mother's last name, right? Like I mean I still remember that
like we were in Florida just you know when we lived in
Florida like 15 years ago or something and I went to pick
up the dry cleaning you know and I said no I don't
have a ticket well maybe my wife dropped it off can you
check under Slavsky? And they said well why would your wife have
a different last name than you? Like it was like you know
like completely unfathomable. So you know I just think that that was
just what I you know but we can do that nowadays. But
what you do by specifically if somebody's father's not Jewish or you
know or don't know who the father is so the רמ"א Rema
brings down the practice of using the mother's mother's father's name but
in the כתובה. Kesubah. But what you could also do you could
just use the mother's name you know but again there was it
was just assumed that of course you identify people in a patriarchy
identify people by their you know by some male by some male
relative's name you know. Let's say I said to you oh well
you know we can't use your father's name let's just use your
brother's name. Why would you use my brother's name? Like right you
know? So it's you know so that's I think just.